from the angut Naya suit called walking
walking walking and it just says if a sensual
walking and it just says if a sensual
thought or thought of ill will or
cruelty arises while walking and if you
tolerate it and do not abandon it then
you are devoid of effort and moral
shame constantly lazy and lacking energy
while walking
and uh it goes on whether walking
standing sitting or lying down one who
uh thinks bad thoughts connected with
household life has entered upon the
wrong path infatuated by delusive things
such a person cannot be free but one who
has his thoughts calmed and delights in
stilling of thought such a person can be
free so there a lot of uh walking
meditation out there people like to do
but it's they focus on the the feeling
of their feet on the sand yeah not the
actual nature of the thinking yeah it's
quite common and that's you know walk
from this point to that point how many
steps 30 St same for anybody posture by
the sit well when the will says he's
upon the wrong path means he's going
down the wrong
direction that's what it means in a more
in a more most accurate manner so going
down the wrong path basically attending
to things wrongly and means going down
the wrong direction of your of your
efforts so even the ones who are making
the efforts and that's exactly the
example you gave when uh when you're
doing walking meditation mostly today
people again there after you're after an
again there after you're after an
experience of peace or some some sort of
some sort of
um factual um well you're after
experience of peace or some sort sort of
experience of some novelty or or or or
or the other but
um not many people would use the
meditation to reflect upon the nature of
the thoughts yet that's all the s to
talk about as anything that really
matters is to not uh entertain the UNH
wholesome and to cultivate the wholesome
whether you're sitting walking lying
down or standing whether you're talking
whether you're alone or with people um
but yeah Unfortunately today and you get
this like a like a mass group Retreat
sentence and so on and then you get
thought like walkum meditation You
observe the souls of your feet and you
try to like be as present as possible
and catch the moment and so on all that
is nothing other than just a focusing
practice on a particular aspect of your
body on a particular basically type of
perception of touch that's it and it can
be so it can it can produce a release
for people because most of the most of
the rest of the rest of the time they
spend they spend their the day the day
in an unmindful State very busy very
engaged and then just focusing on one
particular thing and refusing to give
attention to everything else seems like
a way to go because it provides you with
a degree of Peace but that piece is only
relative to your lifestyle beforehand
that piece is not the measure of your
understanding and wisdom that comes if
you do the D correctly and uh it's it's
not hard thing to to see that just see
when you when you're out of the retreat
how much of your composure you can keep
when you go back to your daily life to
to your other things dealing with things
whether you'll still be able to to to
remain uh impenetrable to the UNH
wholesome States as you're walking
sitting lying down or
standing and most people won that's why
they have to keep going back for
Retreats prolonging Retreats doing
longer Retreats more intense Retreats
all that but then they say well if I
focus on my feet walking on the sand
right then
I don't think any sentral thoughts well
that's the thing that's the thing
the where you focus is not the root of
the problem the root of the problem is not
problem the root of the problem is not
understanding the nature of un wholesome
and because of that being subject to it
because you don't know how even
unwittingly you entertain it you fuel it
you feed it which means you end up
acting out of it so think of unh
wholesome thoughts are a problem then
proliferating un wholesome thoughts are
a further problem so what happens when
people do the focusing practice they
would focus on one particular thing and
refuse to give attention to everything
else including the problem the problem
of un
wholesome so then they can feel like
yeah this is really working and I mean
I'm not saying there's absolutely like
no benefit whatsoever but I'm saying the
benefit is only relative for those who
are who are who are distracted most of
the other time distracted with Duty with
family with sensuality or or just with
your views in some cases so the point is
to recognize that like yeah not giving
attention to the problem can help you
but that's not solving the problem
that's just managing it dealing with it
temporarily and that's exactly the point
you can practice and further this type
of focusing meditation only in such
Retreat settings you can't sustain that
out in the world or you can't sustain
that if you have to climb up and down
the mountain every single day for penda
but for 5 kilm in rain or what whatever
else you can try but you're going to
burn out very soon as you see many many
many cases that that well we both kind
of witnessed with the mon who would go
in the great seclusion focused on some
sort of technique to do it and then just
after a week or two you can't handle it
anymore you need you need something you
need some reference point because okay
now you stopped attending you're just
focusing on one thing but that's it
that's that that's a w that's a dead end
so the only benefit you were getting
before from your meditation practice
wasn't because of what you were focusing
on it's because of what you were not
focusing on which was the UN wholesome
you were not focusing on un wholesome
that was the piece you were getting now
you arrived and not focusing on un
wholesome because you're focusing on
something else which sooner or later
environment will prevent you to do so or
you're just going to run out of the of
the most obvious inspiration to do so
and then what you're going to do you
just back in the same un wholesome which
remain intact cuz you you haven't been U
understand understanding it Discerning
it resolving it you've been ignoring it
through watching the SES of your feet
through watching the tip of your nose
and so on so that's what I mean nobody
denies that people can experience
peaceful feelings when they do focusing
meditation but the point here is that
won't result in approving the problem
it's only covering it up it'll be the
same you can only approve the problem if
you if you have if you start looking at
it for what it is
directly and that's exactly what the
quote what the part of the suit Urus
talks about so that's where you
recognize the work is not about me doing
walking meditation for 8 hours a day or
or focusing on my nostrils all the time
the work is recognizing whether the mind
is affected by ill will affected by
greed affected by delusion affected by
UNH wholesome States and then not
entertaining that doesn't matter whether
I'm walking sitting lying down or
standing what posture yeah the posture
is your reference point that you don't
need to interfere Fe with if you know
where the problem is and the problem is
mind affected by un
wholesome so indeed sometimes when it's
just too much to deal with yeah just
ignore it just don't pay any attention
to it until it CES down so that you can
go back to it and deal with
it
but adopting a practice of just
constantly not looking at the problem
and focusing on something else as a way
of release from the problem it's not
going to resolve anything cu there's
absolutely no discernment there no
wisdom no understanding cuz you're not
looking at it distraction it's a form of
distraction that's why that's what the
Buddha did say U when he gave that Sim
it says
um not being free uh not being free from
sensuality these SOS and brahans they
premeditate mism meditate over meditate
under meditate but they don't meditate
and it gives a simile it says they are
like like an owl hunting for a mouse or
a cat waiting to PS on a fish or or or
or or simul basically simulus of praying
upon something or focusing on one moment
where you act where you catch it where
you grab
it and he said that's a that's
meditating with sensuality that's
looking completely down the wrong
path so so that's again just imagine
yourself praying upon something you're
waiting for I don't know a mouse to come
out of this hole you mustn't skip a bat
cuz he might Escape you and see whether
that's different from when people try to
not skip a beat when they're observing
the SS of their feet or not skip a beat
when they're focusing on the nostrils or
the belly movement or whatever you end
up cultivating the same attitude of
praying upon something praying upon
something that you clearly think has
value it's going to resolve all your
problems catching this mouse will fix
all my problems catching these perfect
moments that come and go in front of me
will purify my
mind but that's a completely he said
people who meditate like that meditate
with sensuality that's why they
premeditate mism meditate over meditate
under meditate and so on but they don't
meditate so as you walking a a thought
of Cruelty
arises and you don't tolerate it which
means yeah which means you don't like
thought of Cruelty arises means there is
your work there for you in its entirety
thought of Cruelty that's the problem
nothing else so you don't you don't stop
everything You' be doing you don't you
like just give it all up because I will
never I I I don't want ever to have such
thoughts again you can't do that because
well it's not up to you those thoughts
will be presenting themselves so the in
order for for you to not be victim of
those presentations of ill will or
sensuality you need to understand how
you engage with them and you want to
understand the habits of your engagement
with those thoughts while they're
simultaneously present there if your
sole response to that is look away it's
just look away just ignore it just just
concent my breath concent my breath stop
thinking about it stop thinking about it
and on top of that you're going to wind
yourself up much more because thinking
that you must stop thinking is another
thought that you're thinking in order to
not think so that's why it becom so intense
think so that's why it becom so intense
and sort of uh unpleasant soon as you
have a thought of said cruelty and you
you recognize that you recognize the
thought of Cruelty but then it stops in
a way that's enough very often sometimes
your recognition might not be clear
enough so then you need to endure it you
have to recognize whereby how much of
the thought arises on its own and then
you have to recognize where the where
the line is where if you cross then it's
you doing it you entertaining it you
getting involved with it you trying to
get rid of it all of those are ways of
fueling the
thought including you actively trying to
ignore it why would like there is a
thought in you I must focus on my Souls
of my feet why cuz you're trying to
avoid the Arisen thought in your mind
that you think you must not
have and by trying to
avoid things that are disagreeable to
you what are you doing you're doing
exactly the thing you shouldn't be doing
acting out of craving in regard to how
you're feeling
there is the unpleasant feeling get rid
of it get rid of it get rid of it there
is the pleasant feeling I must have it
longer I must have it longer there's a
recognition that this is the cruel
thought exactly that's not you're doing
the cruel thought presented itself it's
a cruel thought it's not mine this is a
cruel it's like somebody comes right
here in front of your door and this is a
public space yeah your C is yours they
can't come in but they have every right
to stand in front of your cie but if you
feel affected by that that's on you so
if you come out of your C and start to
chase them well now you actually went
into something that's not your domain
not your ownership and trying to control
it which means you left good unattended
and then other things can come
in cuz you're everywhere and
nowhere and the same in the same manner
the thing cannot come in whatever
thought is unless you invited in unless
you drag it in and that's what happens
with sensuality either sensuality as in
like agreeable desire or or disagreeable
something you want to get rid of it just
comes in front of
you but if it's agreable you are the one
who brings it in if it's disagreeable
you are the one who goes out and tries
to chase it either way you overstep your
boundary and because of that you're
subjected to it and that's why you're
affected by
it so that's what there's that another
Su where the Buddha did say um while he
was still on in light bodh when he was
in the it's called fear and dread IM
where he said uh you'll be staying in
this in this frightening forest and
grows with wild animals and then he
would be doing walking meditation at
night and he said if there is a if he
would hear some sound or something or
have a frightening
thought he wouldn't change what he was
doing which is walk with he wouldn't
stop walking sorry he wouldn't stop
walking until he dispels that un
wholesome state of mind and then he
might change the posture in the same
manner whether he was seated standing
sitting or lying down he wouldn't change
the posture before unless he first
removed the UNH wholesome state that are
Isen and you remove the UNH wholesome
state by not acting out of it by not
trying to get rid of it by not trying to
prolong it and that's exactly what it
means I wouldn't change the posture
until this state is d
spelled because if if the UNH wholesome
State came up and now he stopped walking
and done something else means he acted
out of it and that's already a way of
fueling it whether you acted out of it in the
it whether you acted out of it in the
forms of trying to prolong it as in UNH
wholesome state of sensuality or trying
to to to deny it get rid of it as
quickly as possible uh as in un
wholesome state of will will or fear or
or anything uh
disagreeable so the point is you
recognize and and then how much of it
arises on its own and then you don't
either add to it or take away from it
and when it subsides then you change the
posture so if you do that long enough if
you do that long enough any no matter
how subtle ways of fueling the UN
wholesome states of your mind you've
been entertaining they will all fade cuz
you you just you're uprooting it left
and right Bit by Bit by Bit mean you can
appro things but it takes time for them
to to sort of Wither and
die but one thing for sure they'll never
wither and die and you certainly never
approv to them if you keep looking
elsewhere if you keep focusing on your
nostrils for the sake of avoiding the
thought and not having think about
anything and not having to experience
displeasure if you keep focusing on the
SS of your feet because you're trying to
catch a perfect moment and develop this
ultimate peace they will never be
disturbed the the N disturbance doesn't
come from not experiencing disturbing
things non-disturbance comes from not
being disturbed by the disturbing
things so for as long as you're
concerned with the disturbing things not
with your response in regard to
disturbing things you're looking in the
wrong direction you are down the wrong path
distraction work to work to study yeah
through meditation techniques playing
games something to do basically you're
focused on doing things staring at
things of perceiving things and
observing things but not looking your
attitude behind that the intentionality
behind the motivation behind the craving
behind craving is always behind it's
always in regard to so if you never look
in that direction of that background
you're never going to see it because
again uh this
idea is that by being in a particular
posture cross leg Lotus position back
straight spine erect loose and loose
belly and all this all these
posturings that doesn't do the work for
you but that is it's a game that you
play to distract yourself it's a little
ritual little motion motions you go
through to create the significance of
what you're about to do because if you
just sit down stare at the wall or look
down the hill and contemplate why do you
suffer when there is a when you can't
fulfill your desires or why do you
suffer when you experience something
disagreeable why do you suffer when you
pair with things you don't want why do
you suffer when you're separated from
things you
want yeah there's not much to it that
you can
perform and it's it's for many people
it's it's almost just abstract so they
need something more
palpable uh which is on on a level of of
of of sort of mechanical performance
doing things with your body particular
portion particular way of walking I must
be stepping on the outsides of my Souls
of whatever I can't be walking like this
I must walk slowly I can't walk fast all
of that is being concerned with a
particular with a particular content of
your perception failing to see the
nature behind it and certainly failing
to to to recognize the enduring feeling
in regard to
it yes
athletic athletic meditation how how
long can you sit 2 hours well some guys
can sit for 2 weeks well it's all based
as I said it's all it all revolves
around trying to perceive trying to
catch praying upon something and that's
why you would have to go through these
specialized motions cuz if you walk too
fast you can't be catching something so
you must walk slowly slow down stand
stand and just look at it just just just
grab it as it comes out recognize it and
that's it and that's nothing else than
it and that's nothing else than
meditating with that same sensuality
that you're trying to overcome so if
there's no no un wholesome
thoughts AR